So, emotionally and dynamically, this
song is like a masterpiece. It begins
with his mom saying how much Tyler looks
like his father.
>> You got that [__] feet. You got that
[__] body.
>> Think about that dynamic. Think about as
a kid hearing that you look like a guy
that you've never met and thinking most
of your life that he abandoned you,
which is really important to remember
when we get to the end of this song.
This is scored with a really simple
childlike piano. [music]
It almost to me feels like a kid, a
little kid at the piano. So that kind of
sets the stage. And then from here,
Tyler enters the song.
[music]
>> And this is the important part about
this song. You think it's a song about
Tyler's father. It's actually a song
about Tyler's mom. He's singing directly
to his mom throughout this entire song.
Mama, I'm chasing a ghost. I don't know
who he is. To me, that mama is doing so
much emotional work. It evokes like a
vulnerability, calling out to your
mother. And then one of my favorite
moments of the song is when he switches
from piano into the full arrangement.
[music]
And if you listen in the background,
you're going to hear what to my ear
sounds like a theman. It dates back to
like the 30s or something, but has
always been associated with
extraterrestrial. This was like the
go-to instrument for aliens or ghosts.
And in this song, he's singing about a
ghost. I'm chasing a ghost, which is my
father. Second verse, he's singing
directly to his mom. You gave me love
and affection, attention, protection. I
would never judge you cuz everything
worked out without him. He is speaking
to his mom almost as if like he's
forgiving her. He is foreshadowing the
bomb that drops at the end of this song.
Then we get to like the big outro
[music]
and we get a huge big climax at the end.
Musically, we think we have hit the
emotional and musical peak of this song.
But the real peak is the post outro
where everything drops out and his mom
returns to the song and we hear this.
>> It was my fault, not yours. Not his. It
was my fault. I'm sorry. you know,
>> she says here, "He's a good guy. Don't
hold it against him because it was my
fault." And then she ends the song
saying, "Just, you know, forgive me."
>> Yeah.
>> And what Tyler has done throughout this
entire song is forgive his mother.
That's what those verses I think are
about is him saying, "I would never
judge you for this thing that I know you
now did, which was hide my father from
me."
>> Yeah.
>> Which is emotionally I'm getting choked
up just even thinking about that
dynamic. This to me, this outro is like
a great movie. At the end of the story,
multiple character arcs are resolved in
one event. Tyler forgives his mother.
Tyler, I think, absolves his dad as the
villain.
>> Yeah.
>> And Tyler finds himself, I think, finds
closure in forgiving his mother and
presumably his father because now he
knows that it actually was his father
did want to be in his life. maybe the
most powerful moment emotionally in his
entire catalog.